[MUSIC]
[음악]
So let's take this TF IDF's, and do a couple of fun things with them.
이 TF-IDF로 재밌는 일을 해보죠
So first, we're gonna manually,
먼저
okay, so let me just type in here.
여기 적어넣죠
So we're gonna manually compute
직접 몇 사람 간의 거리를
distances between a few people.
손으로 계산합니다
So the goal here is just to show what those distances look like,
이것의 목표는 거리를 통해
just to get a sense of what we're learning from TF IDF.
TF-IDF로부터 배울 점을 엿보기 위함이죠
So for example, let's take three people.
세 사람을 예로 들어보죠
So we already talked about Obama.
오바마는 이미 해봤죠
We already have that Obama variable in there.
오바마 변수는 이미 갖고 있습니다
Let's create two new variables.
변수 둘을 새로 생성해보죠
Let's say Clinton, which are the people I'm going to select one.
클린턴으로는 인물 중
The person whose name is equal
이름이 미국의 전 대통령인
to Bill Clinton, the former US President.
빌 클린턴인 사람을 고릅니다
Let's select another person, so for example, let's select Beckham.
또 다른 인물을 들어보죠 베컴을 예로 들어보겠습니다
So, Beckham is a famous British,
베컴은 유명한 영국의
English footballer and so,
축구선수인데
we're gonna select out of the people,
인물 중에서
the person whose name is equal to,
이름이 데이비드 베컴인 사람을
his name is actually David Beckham.
골라냅니다
Now that we selected Clinton and Beckham, let's compute the similarity between those
클린턴과 베컴을 골랐으니 이 두 사람과
two people, and the President, Barack Obama.
바락 오바마 대통령 간의 거리와 계산해봅시다
So, what we gonna do is ask the question.
이로써 우리는 오바마가 클린턴에 가까운지
Is Obama closer to
베컴에 가까운지에
Clinton than to Beckham?
답할 수 있습니다
Okay a little mistake here.
실수가 있었네요
So is Obama closer to Clinton than to Beckham?
오바마가 베컴보다 클린턴에 더 가까울까요?
Now there are various ways to measure similarity or
두 벡터, 문서 사이의 유사도나 거리를
distances between two vectors, or in this case two documents.
측정하는 방법은 다양합니다
We computed the TF IDF's.
TF-IDF를 계산합니다
And what we're gonna do is compute the distance between
클린턴, 오바마 문서 간의 거리를
these different documents, the one about Clinton, the one about Obama and so on.
계산합니다
So I'm gonna use distance metrics that are already
GraphLab Create에 이미 구현된
implemented inside the GraphLab Create so we don't have to implement them ourselves.
거리 기준을 쓸 것이라 새로 구현할 필요가 없습니다
So we need to look at graphlab.distances and press Tab,
graphlab.distances까지 치고 탭을 누르면
you'll see several options here.
여러 선택지가 뜹니다
The Clinton distance that we talked about in class, cosine distance,
강의에서 설명드렸던 코사인 거리,
jaccard similarity, and so on that we're gonna see throughout this specialization.
자카드 유사도 등을 앞으로도 계속 보게 됩니다
We're gonna use cosine distance.
이번엔 코사인 거리를 쓰도록 하지요
And just as a little note, normally we think about cosine similarity,
들어본 적이 있다면
if you've heard of it.
참고로 코사인 유사도에선
Where the higher the number the more similar two articles are.
숫자가 클수록 두 문서가 유사합니다
Here, we have a distance version of this number, so the lower the better.
하지만 이건 거리라서 낮을수록 좋습니다
The lower the cosine distance, the closer the articles are.
코사인 거리가 낮을수록 문서가 비슷합니다
So the question is, what is the cosine distance between Obama's
그렇다면 오바마의 TF-IDF와
tfidf and that of Clinton?
클린턴의 TF-IDF 간의 코사인 거리는 어떨까요?
But notice that I have selected the column tfidf, and I have to have the little 0
TF-IDF 열을 선택하고 0을 끝에 붙여주는데
at the end here, because it is the zeroth row of this table.
이 표의 0번째 열이기 때문입니다
The table only has one element in it, but
이 표에는 원소가 하나밖에 없지만
we still have to say what row of the table we're looking at.
여전히 열을 지정해줘야 합니다
And so we're gonna compare the Obama tfidf with the Clinton tfidf.
오바마의 TF-IDF를 클린턴의 TF-IDF와 비교합니다
Also at 0, in terms of the cosine distance, and
여기도 0를 붙여줘야 하죠
you see that the distance is 0.83.
코사인 거리는 0.83이 나왔습니다
Now, the question is, what is the distance between,
그렇다면 같은 코사인 거리를 기준으로
in the same metric in the cosine distance, between Obama and Beckham?
오바마와 베컴 사이의 거리는 어떻게 될까요?
So I'm gonna type Obama
오바마 TF-IDF의
tfidf, computed at 0,
0번째 열과
with Beckham's tfidf, also at 0.
베컴 TF-IDF의 0번째 열이죠
And you'll see that this distance is 0.97.
거리는 0.97로 계산됩니다
The biggest distance you can get is 1.0, in fact.
최대 거리가 1.0이니
And so in this case, Obama
예상대로 오바마는 베컴보다 클린턴에
is much closer to Clinton than he is to Beckham, which makes a lot of sense.
훨씬 가깝습니다
But we've done this just manually for a few people, how do we
몇 사람을 대상으로 직접 계산해봤는데
automate this process of finding out how close an article is to other articles.
한 문서를 다른 문서와 비교하는 과정을 자동화하려면 어떻게 할까요?
And in this case how close is a person to other people.
우리의 경우 사람과 사람이 얼마나 비슷한지가 되겠죠
In the lectures, Emily talked about nearest neighbor models and
강의에서 에밀리가 최근접 이웃 모델과
how they can be used for document retrieval.
이를 통한 문서 검색을 설명했습니다
So today we're gonna actually do some cool document retrieval using
오늘은 간단한 최근접 이웃 모델을 통한
a simple nearest neighbor model.
멋진 문서 검색을 해보죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]